<resources>
    <string name="app_name">FamousScientist</string>
    <string-array name="biographyMathematicians">


    <item> al-Khwārizmī, in full Muḥammad ibn Mūsā al-Khwārizmī, (born c. 780 —died c. 850),
        Muslim mathematician and astronomer whose major works introduced Hindu-Arabic numerals and the concepts of
        algebra into European mathematics. Latinized versions of his name and of his most famous book title live on
        in the terms algorithm and algebra.

Al-Khwārizmī lived in Baghdad, where he worked at the “House of Wisdom” (Dār al-Ḥikma) under the caliphate of
        al-Maʾmūn. The House of Wisdom acquired and translated scientific and philosophic treatises, particularly
        Greek, as well as publishing original research. Al-Khwārizmī’s work on elementary algebra,
        Al-Kitāb al-mukhtaṣar fī ḥisāb al-jabr waʾl-muqābala (“The Compendious Book on Calculation by
        Completion and Balancing”), was translated into Latin in the 12th century, from which the title and
        term algebra derives. Algebra is a compilation of rules, together with demonstrations, for finding
        solutions of linear and quadratic equations based on intuitive geometric arguments, rather than the
        abstract notation now associated with the subject. Its systematic, demonstrative approach distinguishes
        it from earlier treatments of the subject. It also contains sections on calculating areas and volumes of
        geometric figures and on the use of algebra to solve inheritance problems according to proportions
        prescribed by Islamic law. Elements within the work can be traced from Babylonian mathematics of the
        early 2nd millennium BCE through Hellenistic, Hebrew, and Hindu treatises.


    </item>
        <item>
        Euclid, Greek Eukleides, (flourished c. 300 BCE, Alexandria, Egypt),
        the most prominent mathematician of Greco-Roman antiquity, best known for
        his treatise on geometry, the Elements.
Of Euclid’s life nothing is known except what the Greek philosopher
        Proclus (c. 410–485 CE) reports in his “summary” of famous Greek
        mathematicians. According to him, Euclid taught at Alexandria in the
        time of Ptolemy I Soter, who reigned over Egypt from 323 to 285 BCE.
        Medieval translators and editors often confused him with the philosopher
        Eukleides of Megara, a contemporary of Plato about a century before, and therefore called him Megarensis. Proclus supported his date for Euclid by writing “Ptolemy once asked Euclid if there was not a shorter road to geometry than through the Elements, and Euclid replied that there was no royal road to geometry.” Today few historians challenge the consensus that Euclid was older
        than Archimedes (c. 290–212/211 BCE).

    </item>
        <item>
     Leonhard Euler, (born April 15, 1707, Basel, Switzerland—died September 18, 1783, St. Petersburg, Russia),
    Swiss mathematician and physicist, one of the founders of pure mathematics. He not only made decisive and
    formative contributions to the subjects of geometry, calculus, mechanics, and number theory but also developed
    methods for solving problems in observational astronomy and demonstrated useful applications of mathematics in
    technology and public affairs.

</item>
        <item>
        Carl Friedrich Gauss, original name Johann Friedrich Carl Gauss, (born April 30, 1777, Brunswick
        [Germany]—died February 23, 1855, Göttingen, Hanover), German mathematician, generally regarded as one of
        the greatest mathematicians of all time for his contributions to number theory, geometry, probability theory,
        geodesy, planetary astronomy, the theory of functions, and potential theory (including electromagnetism).

Gauss was the only child of poor parents. He was rare among mathematicians in that he was a calculating prodigy,
        and he retained the ability to do elaborate calculations in his head most of his life.
        Impressed by this ability and by his gift for languages, his teachers and his devoted mother
        recommended him to the duke of Brunswick in 1791, who granted him financial assistance to continue
        his education locally and then to study mathematics at the University of Göttingen from 1795 to 1798.
        Gauss’s pioneering work gradually established him as the era’s preeminent mathematician, first in the
        German-speaking world and then farther afield, although he remained a remote and aloof figure.
     </item>

        <item> Nikolay Ivanovich Lobachevsky, (born Dec. 1 [Nov. 20, Old Style], 1792,
            Nizhny Novgorod, Russia—died Feb. 24 [Feb. 12, Old Style], 1856, Kazan), Russian mathematician and
            founder of non-Euclidean geometry, which he developed independently of János Bolyai and Carl Gauss.
            (Lobachevsky’s first publication on this subject was in 1829, Bolyai’s in 1832; Gauss never published
            his ideas on non-Euclidean geometry.)


Lobachevsky grew up in a family of moderate means. Family relations, however, were evidently strained.
            After 1791 his mother was effectively divorced from her husband, Ivan Lobachevsky.
            Modern analysis of previously unknown archival materials shows that Lobachevsky’s father
            was most likely Sergey Shebarshin (d. 1797), a graduate of Moscow State University who worked
            as a surveyor and rose to the rank of titular councilor. After Shebarshin’s death the economic
            circumstances of the family worsened. From 1802 Lobachevsky lived in Kazan, where he studied on
            a government scholarship at the Gymnasium and after 1807 at Kazan State University, which
            had been opened in the same building by Tsar Alexander I in 1804.

   </item>
        <item> Blaise Pascal, (born June 19, 1623, Clermont-Ferrand, France—died
            August 19, 1662, Paris), French mathematician, physicist,
            religious philosopher, and master of prose. He laid the
            foundation for the modern theory of probabilities,
            formulated what came to be known as Pascal’s principle of pressure,
            and propagated a religious doctrine that taught the experience of
            God through the heart rather than through reason.
            The establishment of his principle of intuitionism had an
            impact on such later philosophers as Jean-Jacques Rousseau
            and Henri Bergson and also on the Existentialists.


Pascal’s father, Étienne Pascal, was presiding judge of the tax court at
            Clermont-Ferrand. His mother died in 1626, and in 1631 the
            family moved to Paris. Étienne, who was respected as a
            mathematician, devoted himself henceforth to the education of
            his children. While his sister Jacqueline (born in 1625)
            figured as an infant prodigy in literary circles,
            Blaise proved himself no less precocious in mathematics.
            In 1640 he wrote an essay on conic sections, Essai pour l
            es coniques, based on his study of the now classical work of
            Girard Desargues on synthetic projective geometry.
            The young man’s work, which was highly successful in the
            world of mathematics, aroused the envy of no less a personage
            than the great French Rationalist and mathematician René Descartes.


 </item>
        <item>

      Grigori Perelman, (born 1966, U.S.S.R.), Russian mathematician who was awarded—and declined—the Fields
    Medal in 2006 for his work on the Poincaré conjecture and Fields medalist William Thurston’s geometrization
    conjecture. In 2003 Perelman had left academia and apparently had abandoned mathematics. He was the first
    mathematician ever to decline the Fields Medal.
</item>

        <item>
    Poincaré, (born April 29, 1854, Nancy, France—died July 17, 1912, Paris), French mathematician, one of
        the greatest mathematicians and mathematical physicists at the end of 19th century. He made a
        series of profound innovations in geometry, the theory of differential equations, electromagnetism,
        topology, and the philosophy of mathematics.
    </item>

        <item>
    Siméon-Denis Poisson, (born June 21, 1781, Pithiviers, France—died April 25, 1840, Sceaux),
    French mathematician known for his work on definite integrals, electromagnetic theory, and probability.
</item>

        <item>
    Bernhard Riemann, in full Georg Friedrich Bernhard Riemann, (born September 17, 1826, Breselenz, Hanover
    [Germany]—died July 20, 1866, Selasca, Italy), German mathematician whose profound and novel approaches to
    the study of geometry laid the mathematical foundation for Albert Einstein’s theory of relativity.
    He also made important contributions to the theory of functions, complex analysis, and number theory. </item>

        <item>
        Thales of Miletus, (born c. 624–620 BCE—died c. 548–545 BCE), philosopher renowned as one of the
        legendary Seven Wise Men, or Sophoi, of antiquity. He is remembered primarily for his cosmology based on
        water as the essence of all matter, with Earth a flat disk floating on a vast sea. The Greek historian
        Diogenes Laërtius (flourished 3rd century CE), quoting Apollodorus of Athens (flourished 140 BCE),
        placed the birth of Thales during the 35th Olympiad (apparently a transcription error;
        it should read the 39th Olympiad, c. 624 BCE) and his death in the 58th Olympiad (548–545 BCE)
        at the age of 78 (see philosophy, Western: The pre-Socratic philosophers).

No writings by Thales survive, and no contemporary sources exist. Thus, his achievements are difficult
        to assess. Inclusion of his name in the canon of the legendary Seven Wise Men led to his idealization,
        and numerous acts and sayings, many of them no doubt spurious, were attributed to him,
        such as “Know thyself” and “Nothing in excess.” According to the historian Herodotus (c. 484–c. 425 BCE),
        Thales was a practical statesman who advocated the federation of the Ionian cities of the Aegean region.
        The poet-scholar Callimachus (c. 305–c. 240 BCE) recorded a traditional belief that Thales advised
        navigators to steer by the Little Bear (Ursa Minor) rather than by the Great Bear (Ursa Major),
        both prominent constellations in the Northern Hemisphere. He is also said to have used his knowledge
        of geometry to measure the Egyptian pyramids and to calculate the distance from shore of ships at sea.
        Although such stories are probably apocryphal, they illustrate Thales’ reputation. The poet-philosopher
        Xenophanes (c. 560–c. 478 BCE) claimed that Thales predicted the solar eclipse that stopped the battle
        between King Alyattes of Lydia (reigned c. 610–c. 560 BCE) and King Cyaxares of Media (reigned 625–585 BCE),
        evidently on May 28, 585. Modern scholars believe, however, that he could not possibly have had the
        knowledge to predict accurately either the locality or the character of an eclipse. Thus, his feat was
        apparently isolated and only approximate; Herodotus spoke of his foretelling the year only.
        That the eclipse was nearly total and occurred during a crucial battle contributed considerably to
        his exaggerated reputation as an astronomer.

Thales has been credited with the discovery of five geometric theorems: (1) that a circle is bisected by its
        diameter, (2) that angles in a triangle opposite two sides of equal length are equal, (3) that opposite
        angles formed by intersecting straight lines are equal, (4) that the angle inscribed inside a semicircle
        is a right angle, and (5) that a triangle is determined if its base and the two angles at the base are
        given. His mathematical achievements are difficult to assess, however, because of the ancient practice of
        crediting particular discoveries to men with a general reputation for wisdom.




    </item>

        <item>

    Cédric Villani, (born October 5, 1973, Brive-la-Gaillarde, France), French mathematician and politician who
        was awarded the Fields Medal in 2010 for his work in mathematical physics.
    </item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="urlMathematicians">
        <item> https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Khw%C3%A2rizm%C3%AE    </item>

        <item> https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclid   </item>


        <item> https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonhard_Euler
</item>

        <item>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Friedrich_Gauss </item>

        <item> https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikola%C3%AF_Ivanovitch_Lobatchevski </item>

        <item>   https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blaise_Pascal  </item>
        <item>
    https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grigori_Perelman </item>

        <item>
    https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_Poincar%C3%A9
    </item>
        <item>
    https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sim%C3%A9on_Denis_Poisson
 </item>

        <item>

    https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernhard_Riemann
</item>
        <item>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thales_of_Miletus</item>

        <item>
    https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%C3%A9dric_Villani
</item>
    </string-array>


    <string name="image_width"> wrap_content </string>

</resources>
